Let's imagine a sculptor building a statue,
دعونا نتخيل نحاتاً يقوم بنحت تمثال،
just chipping away with his chisel.
يحفر الرقاقات بإزميله.
Michelangelo had this elegant way of describing it when he said,
كان لدى (مايكل أنجلو) طريقة أنيقة في وصف ذلك حينما قال،
"Every block of stone has a statue inside of it,
"كل كتلة من الحجر تحمل تمثالاً بداخلها،
and it's the task of the sculptor to discover it."
و مهمة النحات اكتشاف ذلك"
But what if he worked in the opposite direction?
ولكن ماذا لو كان يعمل في الاتجاه المعاكس؟
Not from a solid block of stone,
ليس في كتلة صلبة من الحجر،
but from a pile of dust,
لكن في كومة من الغبار،
somehow gluing millions of these particles together to form a statue.
وبطريقة ما يقوم بلصق الملايين من تلك الذرات معاً ليصنع تمثالاً.
I know that's an absurd notion.
أعلم أنها فكرة سخيفة.
It's probably impossible.
إنها مستحيلة على الأغلب.
The only way you get a statue from a pile of dust
الطريقة الوحيدة للحصول على تمثال من كومة من الغبار
is if the statue built itself --
هي إن قام التمثال ببناء نفسه
if somehow we could compel millions of these particles to come together
لو كنا بطريقة ما قادرين على إجبار الملايين من تلك الذرات على الاجتماع معاً
to form the statue.
لتشكّل التمثال.
Now, as odd as that sounds,
الأن، ورغم غرابة ذلك،
that is almost exactly the problem I work on in my lab.
هذه هي بالضبط تقريباً المشكلة التي أعمل عليها في معملي.
I don't build with stone,
أنا لا أبني بالحجارة،
I build with nanomaterials.
أنا أبني بالمواد النانوية .
They're these just impossibly small, fascinating little objects.
إنها تلك الأشياء المذهلة الصغيرة بشكل لا يمكن تخيله.
They're so small that if this controller was a nanoparticle,
إنها صغيرة جداً لدرجة أنه لو كانت أداة التحكم هذه جزيئاً متناهي الصغر،
a human hair would be the size of this entire room.
فستكون الشعرة البشرية بحجم هذه الغرفة.
And they're at the heart of a field we call nanotechnology,
وهي الأساس فى مجال نسميه تكنولوجيا النانو،
which I'm sure we've all heard about,
وأنا متأكد من كوننا سمعنا به جميعاً،
and we've all heard how it is going to change everything.
وسمعنا جميعاً كيف أنه سيغير كل شيء.
When I was a graduate student,
عندما كنت طالب دراسات عليا،
it was one of the most exciting times to be working in nanotechnology.
كان هذا أحد أكثر الأوقات إثارة للعمل في مجال تكنولوجيا النانو.
There were scientific breakthroughs happening all the time.
كانت هناك اكتشافات علمية تحدث طوال الوقت.
The conferences were buzzing,
كانت المؤتمرات تضجّ،
there was tons of money pouring in from funding agencies.
كانت الكثير من الأموال تصب من المؤسسات الممولة.
And the reason is
والسبب هو
when objects get really small,
عندما تصبح المواد صغيرة جداً،
they're governed by a different set of physics that govern ordinary objects,
فهي تخضع لفيزياء مختلفة عن التي تحكم المواد العادية،
like the ones we interact with.
مثل تلك التي نتعامل معها.
We call this physics quantum mechanics.
يطلق على هذه االفيزياء (ميكانيكا الكم).
And what it tells you is that you can precisely tune their behavior
وما تخبرك به هو أن بإمكانك ضبط سلوكها بدقة
just by making seemingly small changes to them,
بمجرد إجراء تعديلات طفيفة عليها،
like adding or removing a handful of atoms,
مثل إضافة أو إزالة حفنة من الذرات،
or twisting the material.
أو ثني المادة.
It's like this ultimate toolkit.
إنها تشبه حقيبة الأدوات المتكاملة.
You really felt empowered; you felt like you could make anything.
كنت تشعر بالقوة حقاً؛ تشعر أن بإمكانك عمل أي شيء.
And we were doing it --
وكنا نقوم بعمل ذلك
and by we I mean my whole generation of graduate students.
وبـ (كنا) أعني جيلي الكامل من طلبة الدراسات العليا.
We were trying to make blazing fast computers using nanomaterials.
كنا نحاول صنع أجهزة حاسوب فائقة السرعة باستخدام المواد متناهية الصغر.
We were constructing quantum dots
كنا نشيد نقاطاً كمية
that could one day go in your body and find and fight disease.
يمكنها في يوم ما أن تدخل إلى جسدك وتحارب الأمراض.
There were even groups trying to make an elevator to space
حتى أنه كانت هناك مجموعات تحاول صناعة مصعد إلى الفضاء
using carbon nanotubes.
باستخدام أنابيب النانو الكربونية.
You can look that up, that's true.
يمكنكم البحث عن ذلك، إنه حقيقي.
Anyways, we thought it was going to affect
على أي حال، ظننا أن الأمر كان سيؤثر
all parts of science and technology, from computing to medicine.
على جميع أجزاء العلم والتكنولوجيا، من الحوسبة وحتى الطب.
And I have to admit,
ويجب أن أعترف،
I drank all of the Kool-Aid.
لقد اقتنعت بالفكرة تماماً.
I mean, every last drop.
أعني إلى أقصى حد.
But that was 15 years ago,
لكن ذلك كان قبل 15 عاماً،
and --
و ..
fantastic science was done, really important work.
أُنجزت أعمالا علمية عظيمة، أعمالا مهمة حقاً.
We've learned a lot.
وتعلمنا الكثير.
We were never able to translate that science into new technologies --
لم نكن قادرين أبداً على ترجمة ذلك العلم إلى تكنولوجيات جديدة
into technologies that could actually impact people.
إلى تكنولوجيات قادرة على التأثير على الناس فعلاً.
And the reason is, these nanomaterials --
والسبب هو، أن تلك المواد متناهية الصغر
they're like a double-edged sword.
هي مثل السلاح ذو الحدّين.
The same thing that makes them so interesting --
الأمر ذاته الذي يجعلها مثيرة للاهتمام،
their small size --
حجمها الصغير،
also makes them impossible to work with.
يجعلها مستحيلة لأن تعمل بها.
It's literally like trying to build a statue out of a pile of dust.
الأمر يشبه حرفياً محاولة بناء تمثال من كومة من الغبار.
And we just don't have the tools that are small enough to work with them.
ونحن لا نملك الأدوات الصغيرة بما فيه الكفاية للتعامل معها.
But even if we did, it wouldn't really matter,
لكن حتى لو كانت لدينا، فلن يهم ذلك،
because we couldn't one by one place millions of particles together
لأنه لا يمكننا تجميع ملايين الجزيئات معاً واحدة فواحدة
to build a technology.
لبناء التكنولوجيا.
So because of that,
وبسبب ذلك،
all of the promise and all of the excitement
كل الوعود وكل الإثارة
has remained just that: promise and excitement.
بقيت كما هي: مجرد وعود وإثارة.
We don't have any disease-fighting nanobots,
ليست لدينا أية روبوتات نانو مكافحة للأمراض،
there's no elevators to space,
لا توجد مصاعد إلى الفضاء،
and the thing that I'm most interested in, no new types of computing.
وذلك الأمر الذي يثير اهتمامي أكثر من غيره أنه لاتوجد أنواع جديدة من الحوسبة.
Now that last one, that's a really important one.
وذلك الأمر الأخير، كان مهماً بحق.
We just have come to expect
كنا بدأنا نتوقع
the pace of computing advancements to go on indefinitely.
أن تستمر عجلة التقدم في مجال الحوسبة بلا نهاية.
We've built entire economies on this idea.
لقد قمنا ببناء اقتصاد على هذه الفكرة.
And this pace exists
وهذه العجلة موجودة
because of our ability to pack more and more devices
بسبب قدرتنا على جمع أجهزة أكثر وأكثر
onto a computer chip.
داخل شريحة الكومبيوتر.
And as those devices get smaller,
وبينما تزداد تلك الأجهزة صغراً،
they get faster, they consume less power
فإنها تصبح أسرع وتستهلك طاقة اقل
and they get cheaper.
وتصبح أرخص.
And it's this convergence that gives us this incredible pace.
وهذا الالتقاء هو ما يمنحنا وتيرة التقدم المذهلة هذه.
As an example:
كمثال:
if I took the room-sized computer that sent three men to the moon and back
إن أخذت جهاز كومبيوتر بحجم الغرفة والذي قام بإرسال وإعادة ثلاثة رجال من وإلى القمر
and somehow compressed it --
وقمت بضغطه بطريقة ما،
compressed the world's greatest computer of its day,
قمت بضغط أعظم كومبيوتر في العالم في زمنه،
so it was the same size as your smartphone --
ليصبح بنفس حجم هاتفك الذكي،
your actual smartphone,
هاتفك الذكي الفعلي،
that thing you spent 300 bucks on and just toss out every two years,
ذلك الشيء الذي تنفق 300 دولار عليه ثم تتخلص منه كل سنتين،
would blow this thing away.
سوف يزيح ذلك الشيء بعيداً.
You would not be impressed.
لن يذهلك الأمر.
It couldn't do anything that your smartphone does.
لن يتمكن من القيام بأي عمل يقوم به هاتفك الذكي.
It would be slow,
سيكون بطيئاً،
you couldn't put any of your stuff on it,
لن تضع أياً من أشيائك فيه،
you could possibly get through the first two minutes
من المحتمل أن تتمكن من مشاهدة الدقيقتين الأوليين
of a "Walking Dead" episode if you're lucky --
من حلقة "الموتى السائرون" إن كنت محظوظاً
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
The point is the progress -- it's not gradual.
الأمر هو أن التطور لا يحدث تدريجياً.
The progress is relentless.
التطور لا يهمد.
It's exponential.
إنه يتضاعف.
It compounds on itself year after year,
إنه يتراكب على نفسه سنة بعد سنة،
to the point where if you compare a technology
إلى النقطة التي إن قارنت فيها تكنولوجيا
from one generation to the next,
من جيل إلى الجيل التالي،
they're almost unrecognizable.
فلا يمكنك التعرف عليها تقريباً.
And we owe it to ourselves to keep this progress going.
ونحن ندين لأنفسنا بأن نبقي هذا التطور مستمراً.
We want to say the same thing 10, 20, 30 years from now:
نريد أن نقول الشيء ذاته بعد 10، 20، أو 30 عاماً من الآن:
look what we've done over the last 30 years.
انظروا ماذا فعلنا خلال الـ 30 عاماً الماضية.
Yet we know this progress may not last forever.
لكننا نعلم أن هذا التطور قد لايستمر إلى الأبد.
In fact, the party's kind of winding down.
في الحقيقة، فالحفل يوشك على الانتهاء.
It's like "last call for alcohol," right?
يشبه الأمر النداء الأخير لشُرب الكحول، أليس كذلك؟
If you look under the covers,
إن نظرت تحت الأغطية،
by many metrics like speed and performance,
طبقاً للعديد من المقاييس مثل السرعة والأداء،
the progress has already slowed to a halt.
فالتطور قد تباطأ إلى نقطة التوقف بالفعل..
So if we want to keep this party going,
لذلك إن أردنا الاستمرار بالاحتفال،
we have to do what we've always been able to do,
فعلينا القيام بما كنا قادرين على فعله دائماً،
and that is to innovate.
وهو أن نبتكر.
So our group's role and our group's mission
وبالتالي دورنا ومهتنا كمجموعة
is to innovate by employing carbon nanotubes,
أن نبتكر باستخدام أنابيب النانو الكربونية،
because we think that they can provide a path to continue this pace.
لأننا نعتقد أنها تستطيع منحنا طريقا للتقدم بسرعة.
They are just like they sound.
إنها مشابها لاسمها.
They're tiny, hollow tubes of carbon atoms,
إنها صغيرة جدا وأنابيب مجوفة من الذرات الكربونية
and their nanoscale size, that small size,
ومقياسها النانومتري، وبهذا الحجم الصغير،
gives rise to these just outstanding electronic properties.
تعطي تطورا لهذه الخصائص الإلكترونية المتميزة.
And the science tells us if we could employ them in computing,
ويخبرنا العلم أننا إذا طبقنا هذه التقنية فى مجال الحوسبة،
we could see up to a ten times improvement in performance.
فيمكن أن نحدث تطورا عشرات المرات فى الأداء.
It's like skipping through several technology generations in just one step.
إنها بمثابة قفزة من أجيال مختلفة من التكنولوجيا فى خطوة واحدة.
So there we have it.
لذا وقد حصلنا عليها
We have this really important problem
فعندنا مشكلة حقيقة كبيرة
and we have what is basically the ideal solution.
وعندنا بالأساس الحل المثالي.
The science is screaming at us,
يصيّح العلم فينا ويقول،
"This is what you should be doing to solve your problem."
"هذا ما يجب أن تفعله لحل مشكلتك."
So, all right, let's get started,
لذا،حسنا دعونا نبدأ،
let's do this.
هيا نقوم بهذا.
But you just run right back into that double-edged sword.
فمهما تملصت من هذا فإنها فى النهاية سلاح ذو حدين.
This "ideal solution" contains a material that's impossible to work with.
هذا " الحل المثالي" يحتوي على مادة يستحيل التعامل معها.
I'd have to arrange billions of them just to make one single computer chip.
إذا أنه لا بد من ترتيب البلايين من هذه المواد لصنع شريحة حاسوب واحدة.
It's that same conundrum, it's like this undying problem.
إنها نفس المعضلة، إنها كهذا المشكلة الأبدية.
At this point, we said, "Let's just stop.
وفى هذه المرحلة ، نقول هيا نتوقف.
Let's not go down that same road.
لنتوقف عن الاستمرار فى هذا الطريق.
Let's just figure out what's missing.
هيا نكتشف ما الشيء المفقود.
What are we not dealing with?
ما الشيء الذي لم نتعامل معه؟
What are we not doing that needs to be done?"
وما الذي لم نفعله وتحتاج لفعله؟
It's like in "The Godfather," right?
الأمر كفيلم " العراّب" أليس كذلك؟
When Fredo betrays his brother Michael,
عندما خان فريدو أخاه مايكل،
we all know what needs to be done.
نعرف جميعا ما يجب فعله.
Fredo's got to go.
وقد رحل فريدو.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But Michael -- he puts it off.
لكن مايكل... وضع حدا للأمر
Fine, I get it.
حسنا، فهمت ذلك.
Their mother's still alive, it would make her upset.
فأمهم لا تزال على قيد الحياة وقد يزعجها ذلك.
We just said,
نحن قلنا
"What's the Fredo in our problem?"
"ما علاقة فريدو بمشكلتنا؟"
What are we not dealing with?
وما الذي لم نتعامل معه؟
What are we not doing,
وما الذي لم نفعله،
but needs to be done to make this a success?"
لكن يجب فعله لإنجاز هذا النجاح؟
And the answer is that the statue has to build itself.
والإجابة: يجب على التمثال أن يبني نفسه.
We have to find a way, somehow,
ويجب أن نجد سبيلا لذلك بطريقة ما،
to compel, to convince billions of these particles
لإجبار أو لإقناع البلايين من هذه الذرات
to assemble themselves into the technology.
لتجمع نفسها في التكنولوجيا.
We can't do it for them. They have to do it for themselves.
لا نستطيع فعل ذلك للذرات بأنفسنا. لكن يجب عليها أن تفعل ذلك بنفسها.
And it's the hard way, and this is not trivial,
وإنه لطريق صعب، وفعل ذلك ليس سهلاً،
but in this case, it's the only way.
لكن فى هذه الحالة، لا يوجد طريق سوى طريق واحد.
Now, as it turns out, this is not that alien of a problem.
الآن، كما تبين أن هذه ليست مشكلة غريبة.
We just don't build anything this way.
لا نبني أي شيء بهذه الطريقة.
People don't build anything this way.
ولا النالس يبنون أي شيء بهذه الطريقة.
But if you look around -- and there's examples everywhere --
لكن لو إذا نظرتم حولكم فهناك أمثلة كثيرة في كل مكان
Mother Nature builds everything this way.
الأم الطبيعة تبني أي شيء حولها بهذه الطريقة.
Everything is built from the bottom up.
كل شيء يُبنى من الأسفل للأعلى.
You can go to the beach,
يمكنكم الذهاب للشاطيء،
you'll find these simple organisms that use proteins --
وستجدون تلك الكائنات الحية البسيطة التي تستخدم البروتين...
basically molecules --
تحديدا الجزيئات...
to template what is essentially sand,
لتشكل قوالب لما هو في الأساس رمل،
just plucking it from the sea
هي فقط تنزعه من البحر
and building these extraordinary architectures with extreme diversity.
وتبني تلك أشكالا معمارية رائعة بهذا التنوع الشديد.
And nature's not crude like us, just hacking away.
والطبيعة ليست بارعة مثلنا، هي فقط تقوم بعملها.
She's elegant and smart,
إنها متحمسة وذكية،
building with what's available, molecule by molecule,
فالبناء بما هو متاح جزيئا بجزيىء،
making structures with a complexity
يصنع هياكل معقدة
and a diversity that we can't even approach.
ومختلفة فلا تستطيع حتى الاقتراب منها
And she's already at the nano.
وهي تعمل بالفعل بتقنية النانو.
She's been there for hundreds of millions of years.
إنها هناك منذ مئات الملايين من السنين.
We're the ones that are late to the party.
نحن الذين تأخرنا فى الاكتشاف.
So we decided that we're going to use the same tool that nature uses,
وبالتالي قررنا أن نستخدم نفس الاداة التى تستخدمها الطبيعة،
and that's chemistry.
وهذه هي الكيمياء.
Chemistry is the missing tool.
الكيمياء هي الأداة المفقودة.
And chemistry works in this case
وتعمل الكيمياء بهذه الحالة
because these nanoscale objects are about the same size as molecules,
لأن هذه الأشياء النانومترية هي تقريبا بنفس حجم الجزيئ،
so we can use them to steer these objects around,
وبالتالي نستطيع استخدامها لتقود تلك الأشياء من حولنا،
much like a tool.
أشبه كثيرا بأداة.
That's exactly what we've done in our lab.
وهذا بالضبط ما فعلنه في مختبرنا.
We've developed chemistry that goes into the pile of dust,
قد طورنا الكيمياء التي تدخل فى كومة من الغبار،
into the pile of nanoparticles,
وفي كومة من جزيئات النانو،
and pulls out exactly the ones we need.
ونسحب الشيء الذي نحتاجه بالضبط.
Then we can use chemistry to arrange literally billions of these particles
فنستخدم الكيمياء لترتيب البلايين من تلك الذرات بالضبط
into the pattern we need to build circuits.
إلى النموذج الذي نحتاجه لبناء دوائر.
And because we can do that,
ولأننا نفعل ذلك،
we can build circuits that are many times faster
نستطيع بناء دوائر تكون أسرع أضعافا مضاعفة
than what anyone's been able to make using nanomaterials before.
أكثر من أي شخص استطاع استخدام مواد النانو من قبل.
Chemistry's the missing tool,
الكيمياء هي الأداة الفقودة،
and every day our tool gets sharper and gets more precise.
وكل يوم تصبح أداتنا حادة وأكثر دقة
And eventually --
وأخيراً...
and we hope this is within a handful of years --
ونأمل أن يحدث هذا في سنين عِددا.
we can deliver on one of those original promises.
يمكن أن نحصل على واحدة من تلك الوعود البديعة.
Now, computing is just one example.
والان،الحوسبة أحد تلك الامثلة.
It's the one that I'm interested in, that my group is really invested in,
وإنها أحد الأشياء التي أهتم بها، وبالفعل تبذل مجموعتي فيها جهدا،
but there are others in renewable energy, in medicine,
لكن هناك أشياء أخرى في الطاقة المتجددة وفي الطب،
in structural materials,
وفي المواد البنائية،
where the science is going to tell you to move towards the nano.
وحيثما يوجد العلم لأنه يحثنا على الاتجاه نحو تقنية النانو.
That's where the biggest benefit is.
وأن هذه هي الفائدة الكبرى.
But if we're going to do that,
لكن إذا لم نستغل فعل ذلك،
the scientists of today and tomorrow are going to need new tools --
فإن علماء اليوم وغداً سيحتاجون إلى أدوات جديدة...
tools just like the ones I described.
فالأدوات كالأشياء التي وصفتها لكم.
And they will need chemistry. That's the point.
وسيحتاجون الكيمياء. وهذا هو الطريق.
The beauty of science is that once you develop these new tools,
فجمال العلم أن تطوروا تلك الأدوات الجديدة،
they're out there.
إنها موجودة هناك بالخارج.
They're out there forever,
إنها هناك بالخارج للأبد،
and anyone anywhere can pick them up and use them,
وأي شخص في أي مكان يستطيع التقاطهم واستخدامهم،
and help to deliver on the promise of nanotechnology.
ويساعد في الوفاء بالوعد في تكنولوجيا النانو.
Thank you so much for your time. I appreciate it.
شكرًا جزيلاً لوقتكم. أقدر لكم ذلك